<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Blog on Aleksandr Guljajev</title>
    <link>http://www.itchyknowsdevs.me/blog/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Blog on Aleksandr Guljajev</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-US</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 19 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://www.itchyknowsdevs.me/blog/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Om.next and what&#39;s next?</title>
      <link>http://www.itchyknowsdevs.me/blog/om.next-and-whats-next/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.itchyknowsdevs.me/blog/om.next-and-whats-next/</guid>
      <description>I enjoy writing Clojure, a lot. I&amp;rsquo;ve written Javascript, PHP, Python, C, and Go. Clojure is by far the most satisfying language to write code and reason in. I keep coming back to it. Whether it&amp;rsquo;s the kind of people it attracts, alien ideas it encourages implementing things in, or simply personal biased preference, I don&amp;rsquo;t know.
That also extends to Clojurescript. Clojurescript and Clojure have been my first combo in writing front and back-end apps.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Refactoring business-critical PHP application with RabbitMQ</title>
      <link>http://www.itchyknowsdevs.me/blog/refactoring-business-critical-php-application-with-rabbitmq/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 06 Aug 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.itchyknowsdevs.me/blog/refactoring-business-critical-php-application-with-rabbitmq/</guid>
      <description>NB: Code accompanying the post is on github.com/alex-glv/bunny-acme
The Problem While doing contract work optimizing and improving stability of an old PHP-based billing application I was constantly facing issues with long running processes that failed and couldn&amp;rsquo;t easily restore their state.
The actual process was performing daily billing services based on subscription rules.
The process would start, extract a whole bunch of information at once and start processing it one by one, withou keeping an intermediate progress results.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Developing Golang in NixOS</title>
      <link>http://www.itchyknowsdevs.me/blog/developing-golang-in-nixos/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Mar 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.itchyknowsdevs.me/blog/developing-golang-in-nixos/</guid>
      <description>Why NixOS? The idea of fully reproducible system fascinates me a lot. Part of Getting Things Done philosophy is not to contaminate your head with the little things you have to do, you put them down on a list.
That&amp;rsquo;s why we use password managers, because you don&amp;rsquo;t want to keep all those password from a bazillion websites in your head - you trust something else to keep them. With you development environment it&amp;rsquo;s the same - you build your custom machine and when your drive goes bust, you go: &amp;ldquo;Oh, shit.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hugo on Amazon AWS Lambda integrated with GitHub</title>
      <link>http://www.itchyknowsdevs.me/blog/hugo-on-amazon-aws-lambda-integrated-with-github/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Feb 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.itchyknowsdevs.me/blog/hugo-on-amazon-aws-lambda-integrated-with-github/</guid>
      <description>The Problem I love static website generators. I think it&amp;rsquo;s a great iteration over the old approach before dynamic websites became a de-facto standard.
The most compelling argument towards using static websites is &amp;ldquo;minimum-hosting&amp;rdquo; approach. The only thing you need is a web server and a domain name.
You still have the problem of continuos delivery. If you are anything like me, you don&amp;rsquo;t want to keep rebuilding and deploying your website manually.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Containers are not real</title>
      <link>http://www.itchyknowsdevs.me/blog/containers-are-not-real/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Feb 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.itchyknowsdevs.me/blog/containers-are-not-real/</guid>
      <description>The advent of containers Containers seem to have turned the industry upside down and marching full ahead to become the dominant way of shipping software. To uninitiated mortals, Docker seems to be kind of a strange child. Where does it come from, what&amp;rsquo;s it good at? It looks like VM, but everyone keeps telling us not to compare it to VMs. Even though it gained a massive traction, it still has a long way to go to be a de-facto standard every developer should be familiar with.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>